ALFATEHAH, THE LATE DATO’ MEOR
ABDUL RAHMAN BIN DAENG UDA MOHD HASHIM
GRANDMASTER OF SILAT SENI GAYONG MALAYSIA
THIS STORY IS INSPIRED BY TRUE EVENTS
OF THE LIFE AND STRUGGLES
OF THE LATE DATO' MEOR ABDUL RAHMAN.
SOME EVENTS DEPICTED ARE FICTIONAL
AND DO NOT REPRESENT
ANY REAL INDIVIDUALS OR ACTUAL INCIDENTS
ANY RESEMBLANCE IS PURELY COINCIDENTAL
THIS FILM CONTAINS SCENES THAT MAY DISTURB
OR OFFEND SOME VIEWERS
Fight…!
Get him!
Who else wants to die?
Take him out!
Send the best, the most reliable.
There is nothing better than Muay Thai!
Muay Thai, not dancing!
No wasted moves.
Just fierce attacking!
Wait!
I'm the Red Warrior.
I will prove to you that the Malay's blood
still flows with pride.
Fight…!
It is not customary for a warrior
to strike an opponent
who is already helpless.
If you're scared of dying,
don't enter the ring.
Knowledge is not for showing off,
but for defending yourself
from being insulted.
Show me!
Show me what you have!
Fight…!
-Who is he?
-I don't know.
I guess he plans on getting killed.
Fight…!
My silat are not meant to seek enemies,
let alone kill others,
but to empower my people.
I…
Winning or losing
is not by strength…
but by spirit.
-Meor…!
It's customary when traveling
to mind your behavior and manners.
Remember,
you have a child
and a wife who's counting on you.
Alright, Mom.
Take care, Mom and Dad.
God willing, when the time comes,
I will come home.
Send my regards to Kassim and his family.
-God willing!
-Master.
-Yes.
I would like to ask you to bless
all the knowledge that you have taught me.
Lend me your spirit,
so that it will always be with me.
Train to Singapore.
Passengers can board now!
Sit there, okay?
Fadhillah, sit over there.
The knowledge that I've given you,
use it wisely.
Do not seek trouble.
Do not fight to show power,
not for boasting,
but with wisdom,
to defend oneself, family,
nation, religion, and country.
PASIR PANJANG, SINGAPORE 1939
Grandpa, they're here!
-Peace be upon you.
-You're finally here.
And peace be upon you too.
What to do, Pak Kassim?
The train is late, so we are late.
Mom and Dad send their regards.
Peace be upon them.
Welcome to Pasir Panjang.
The name of this village is Pasir Ria.
Is everyone in Taiping okay?
All praise be to God.
-Let me show you the house.
-Yes.
This is the house. It's very simple.
This is more than enough, Pak Kassim.
All praise to God.
Meor, Mat, Che Som,
if you have any problems,
just look for me at my house.
If you need any help,
just look for Atan.
Thank you, Pak Kassim.
-Uncle Mat, which one is your bag?
-This one.
Come, Uncle Mat.
Let me take you to your room.
Peace be upon you.
And peace be upon you too.
You just got here?
Yes. I was a little late.
The cakes, Minah.
-Be careful, honey.
-Yes.
-Be careful
-Come.
Pak Kassim.
Here are some cakes. Minah made them.
It has already cooled down.
Thank you. You shouldn't have.
You're welcome.
This house is close
to the shops and mosque.
The morning market is not far either.
It's at the end of the village,
near the beach.
If you need anything, look for me.
Alright.
Sorry. What was the name again?
-Yunos.
-I'm Meor.
What are you looking at? Come.
Don't look into people's houses.
Grandma…
Grandmother, please don't leave Fadhillah.
Feel sorry for her.
She's been calling for her grandma.
Who knows what tomorrow will bring?
We trust in God.
I am sure
there must be a fortune for us here.
Fortune for our children.
Our children?
-Chicken…!
-Beef…!
-Peace be upon you.
-Yes, Pak Kassim. How are you?
Praise be to God.
There are meat and bones.
-Buy some.
-Which one do you want?
-I'll take this.
-Rice…!
This has just been slaughtered.
Looks common.
They're all nice and cheap.
Wait, wait.
Come and eat!
What are you doing here?
Get out of here!
Come buy salted fish.
This is two dollars.
This is three dollars.
Keep the change.
You don't want any papayas, Talib?
No, it is fine.
-Thank you. Come again, okay?
-Alright.
Come, come. Come buy these clothes.
They're all nice and cheap.
-Spices!
-Satay, mister. Satay…!
Uncle Mat, I want some sweets.
We have cucumbers.
I want to buy some spices.
-For cooking?
-Spicy or non-spicy?
I want this. A little
of this and this one too.
-This one is spicy. Is that okay?
-Sure.
-Fruits…!
-Sarongs for men and women.
-Chom, I want to buy the newspaper.
-Sarongs! Cheap!
-Cheap!
-Papaya!
-Satay…
-Fruits!
How much is it?
Five cents, madam!
Satay…!
Five cents only!
-Thank you
-You're welcome!
-Satay, madam!
-Here, thank you.
-Alright, madam. Please come again
-Yes.
-Thank you.
-This one.
-Satay…
-I want to buy just a little.
-They're all nice and cheap.
-Bananas!
Fadhillah,
what did you ask Uncle Mat to buy?
-Fruits!
-Sweets!
I'm sorry.
-Fruits. Come and buy fruits
-Spices…
-Uncle Meor!
-Fruits…
There are pumpkins, coconuts.
-There are bananas. Fruits!
-Cendol!
-Want some cendol?
-Sure, give me one.
Sure, please wait.
-Fruits…
-Mayang, where's my cendol?
-Peace be upon you.
-And peace be upon you too.
Meor. This is Pak Haron,
the chief of our village.
-How are you doing?
-Fine, praise be to God.
-Welcome to the village, Mr. Meor.
-Thank you.
-God willing, we'll meet again.
-God willing.
-All right. I am going home now, okay?
-Yes.
All right.
How was it?
Did you sleep well last night?
I was so tired. I slept
like a log, Pak Kassim.
Praise be to God.
Do you want some meat?
-Sure…
-Give us a little.
Atan, please prepare that.
Pak Kassim!
We haven't talked about the rent.
Maybe later.
Wait until you land a job first.
God bless you, Pak Kassim.
God willing.
Vegetables…
There's spinach,
-morning glory, chilies,
-Fadhillah.
bitter gourd.
Meor! Check out my vegetables.
Sweetie.
What's your name?
Fadhillah.
My name is Noni.
-Do you want to play with my dolls?
-Yes!
Go now!
Thank you for the cakes.
I'll return the containers.
It's okay.
Fill it with beef rendang too.
Someone told me
that rendang from Perak is nice.
Honey!
I was just kidding.
But it's fine. Chom can cook it.
Is Taiping like Singapore?
It’s not as big as Singapore.
It's a small town.
I have always lived here, Meor.
I've never been to other places.
If God wills, you'll have your chance.
Pack these for them. Pack it.
-Is spinach okay?
-Sure.
Melor. Melor.
Where are the fishmongers?
Why aren't they here yet?
-The sun has risen.
-Yes.
They are always early,
but I don't know why they are late today.
Osman!
Bring the threadfin breams first.
-Those go bad easily.
-All right!
Good morning.
Hey!
You are grinning!
This one's Dewi.
That one is Nana.
-Do you want some candy?
-I do.
-Thief!
-Thank you.
Thief!
Are you okay?
Move aside…
Stop!
Why are you two fighting?
Oh, mister! It hurts!
Ouch!
-Ouch.
-Here is the thief!
If it were up to me,
I would cut off your hand.
-Enough, miss. Enough.
-It hurts!
This kid's ear will fall off later.
Ouch!
-It hurts.
-Why did you steal?
Vegetables. Vegetables.
Vegetables?
I've never seen you two.
We're actually from Perak.
We just arrived yesterday.
Who's your master?
Didn't you see me chasing that boy?
I didn't notice.
-He's hungry.
-Give it to him.
Do you always come here?
Where are you from?
Sudong Island.
I always come here to sell fish.
Please visit Sudong Island.
It's not far from here.
-Wak…
-If God wills.
You can't make an omelet
without breaking a few eggs.
Good morning, Mr. Singh.
Good morning.
Where do you want to go? Interview?
-Yes.
Go straight. There's a signboard
for the Regimental Office.
-Enter the office.
-Okay.
-Thank you, Mr. Singh.
-All right.
How was it?
Did you get it?
You didn't get the job?
I got it!
Don't play with me.
I'll go and ask them myself.
-I got it!
-You're messing with me.
Don't play with me.
Our dinner is really special tonight.
Yes. A sign of gratitude
for getting a job.
-Why, Mat? Is it not tasty?
-It's tasty.
But I feel embarrassed.
I always eat here.
I feel like I'm burdening you a lot.
You're not a burden, Mat.
I'll be even more upset
if you don't eat enough.
Your mother told me,
"Take care of Mat's food and clothes.
He's never been away from his mother."
Peace be upon you.
-Peace be upon you too.
-Peace be upon you too, Yunos.
Come on. Let's eat together.
Dad.
I'm eating rendang.
I came to get Noni.
Noni hasn't finished eating. Sit down.
Yunos.
That's the rendang from Perak, right?
It smells delicious.
Mus!
What were you saying?
Sometimes, they have
dinner parties at night.
So, we can do part-time work
-as a waiter.
-Yes, I've done that.
I got paid well.
How can I join?
Leave it, Mat.
That's how it is
when you're in a foreign place.
In this universe,
you alone are the most
praiseworthy and the most noble.
Peace be upon you.
Meor, that's enough!
Meor! Enough!
Enough, Meor!
Hey!
Oi!
Uncle Meor punched the thief.
No. The thief fell like this.
Like this.
Don't be too rough.
No. I was just kidding.
Auntie, when will Uncle Meor come home?
Uncle Meor will be back in the evening.
I want to learn how to fight.
Check the carburetor first.
TAIPING, PERAK
-One, two, three,
-One, two, three…
-four, five, six,
-five, six,
-seven, eight.
Let's do number two.
-One, two, three.
Like this. This hand.
Like this.
Try it, Noni.
First, tighten your grip.
Then, attack.
Not just deflect but also break.
Understood?
Once again.
Noni, come here.
Okay, Mat?
Can you manage?
Okay.
That's right.
But you must be careful, Mat.
Because if it's not done right,
this will happen.
And…
your enemy can attack here.
What do you think about kung fu moves?
Perfect your silat first, Mat.
Do you think
silat can compete with kung fu?
Each has its own special features,
Silat, Muay Thai, kung fu.
It's all martial arts.
Not for showing off, Mat.
Peace be upon you.
Peace be upon you too.
How are you, Wak Kusang?
Fine, thank God.
Sorry, we're intruding.
You're not intruding at all.
I brought my men from Sudong Island.
They want to meet the great warrior
from Malaya.
-You shouldn't say that.
-Master.
We all came here
because we want to be
your student, Master Meor.
I'm not a silat master.
With the knowledge you have,
you are much more qualified
compared to the martial arts teachers
I've ever met.
I'm not good at teaching.
I'm not a martial arts teacher.
I'm really sorry.
If you teach us what we saw the other day,
that would already be enough.
Tiger!
Tiger, ready!
When I say one,
the steps are one, two, three.
Three.
Move your left hand to block backwards.
Straighten your right hand.
-Cheers
-Cheers.
-Absolutely.
-Okay.
You must come!
Oops.
-Just skip.
-Of course, man!
Why must he take the job?
David, come here.
Hold on.
Hey, where are you going?
This is our last pay.
What now?
One!
Two!
Three!
One!
Two!
Mat, take over.
Okay, Meor.
May Allah bless Muhammad
May Allah bless him and grant him peace
O Prophet, peace be upon you
O Messenger, peace be upon you
Peace be upon you.
My daughter, Siti Aishah.
-She's so cute.
-Kiss. Kiss Aishah.
We wanted to see her.
Don't do that.
Don't come in a crowd.
She'll feel suffocated.
Gosh, we want to see her.
No matter how advanced humans are,
our culture and customs
should not be forgotten.
United we stand,
divided we fall.
I hope our descendants will remember that.
I think with Meor
and Mat here with us,
our village seems to be thriving.
Right?
That's right.
-Three, four, five…
-Move closer.
-Six, seven, eight…
-Continue
-Nine.
SUDONG ISLAND, SINGAPORE
One, two…
Friends.
The master has arrived.
Meor!
-Peace be upon you
-And peace be upon you too.
-Welcome.
-Thank you.
You're finally here on Sudong Island.
I finally have the chance
to come here, Wak Kusang.
It's okay.
This is Meor.
The warrior I talked about the other day.
-This is my wife.
-How are you?
After we're done eating,
-Wak, take them around the village.
-Sure.
Bendol, share it with the others.
Goodness!
Our village is not big.
There are around 15 families here.
-Do you need my help?
-Sure.
Aisha, look at Mom.
-She feels hot.
-Yes.
All right. The first one. Tiger!
Tiger, ready!
One!
Ready!
Two!
One!
Ready!
Two!
This is our village.
This is our family.
Calm.
I feel small on this earth of Allah.
The real wealth…
is a peaceful life.
May this peace
remain in our lives forever.
Amen.
JAPANESE INVASION
13TH FEBRUARY 1942
That's it, Man. Tie it.
Tie it tightly, Man.
Make sure this is tied too, Man.
Man!
Where are the others?
-How many boats did you get?
-I only got seven.
Are those enough?
I've asked Pak Wahab to find more.
It's okay. You should hurry.
-I want to check on Meor.
-All right!
Just take whatever is important, Chom.
I'm here. I'm here.
Pak Wahab, where are the others?
We don't have enough boats, Yunos.
Let the women and children
get on the boat first.
The boat is over there.
Man, help!
Aishah! Hurry up! Run!
Meor! Chom!
Meor!
Where are they now, Mat?
Sembawang Naval Base was bombed.
Mat! Help me, Mat.
-Come here.
-Pak Wahab.
-Get on the boat.
Go with your mom first.
I'll come later. Hurry up.
-Get on the boat.
-I don't want to.
-Take her with you.
-All right.
-Go. Go, my child!
-I don't want to!
-Talib.
-Yes.
Be careful, Fadhillah.
The boat is ready.
Go on. I don't want to.
Up to you.
Come!
Yunos, where are Minah and Noni?
-They're at Siti's house.
-We need to leave now!
-Go on. I'll go and get Noni.
-Yunos!
Hurry up!
Honey!
Goodness!
-Honey!
-Meor!
Honey!
Meor. Hurry, Meor!
Apit, what are you doing here?
Let's get on the boat. Come!
Hurry, Apit.
Pak Wahab!
Fadhillah!
Fadhillah, jump!
-Atan.
-Yes.
Get the boat to Bukum Island
or Sudong Island.
All right!
Get on the boat, Meor!
Chom!
Eat. Open that.
I'll eat first, Chief.
-We cooked for the guests.
-Pass this drink.
Come inside.
Bring them in.
-Wak!
-Come inside. Sit there.
Give them water.
Wak!
Master Meor has arrived!
-Master Meor has arrived?
-Come inside.
Gosh. Pity my child.
Master.
Master, Wak, Resad and I
are going back to the sea
to see if anyone else survived.
All right. Be careful.
All right. Master.
Wak Kusang.
Excuse me.
-Mat.
-Help.
-Fadhillah!
Help him!
Mat. Sit down first.
-Their boat has overturned.
-Sit down.
You're soaking wet.
Cloth! We need cloth!
You are safe now.
Mat.
What happened there?
Our boat capsized.
Singapore was bombed.
Behind every one of God's plans,
there's a reason.
Earlier on…
I felt powerless, honey.
I won't forgive myself
if anything were to happen
to Fadhillah and Aishah.
He knows you're strong.
I thought I wouldn't see you anymore.
I am…
strong because of you.
For the sake of the children,
you need to be strong,
so that I can be even stronger.
I need to be strong.
They're not back yet?
Chief, they're back.
Resad. Mustapha.
Did you see anyone in the sea?
None.
Mustapha. Yunos?
Chief,
we need to save Pasir Ria.
I'm sure that many more are trapped there.
Yes.
Wak Kusang, prepare all their needs.
All right, Chief!
But I need only a few people.
So that our presence will go unnoticed.
Alright.
Don't cry.
Oh, God.
Come.
-Get up.
-Come.
Come out!
-Bring them to the boat.
-All right.
-Did you hear that?
-Yes, I heard it.
Come on!
Mat!
What's the matter, Siti?
Daud fell.
Meor!
Daud!
Mat and Meor are here.
-Daud.
Daud.
Finally, we're safe.
Siti,
have you seen Yunos, Noni, and Minah?
No, I haven't.
Mat!
Bring them to the boat.
-Meor.
-Mat.
They need you now.
Come, Daud.
Oh, God!
Come.
-Be careful.
Timah!
Sir!
Here!
Paddle!
Mustapha!
-Resad.
-Yes.
-Stay strong!
-Resad!
Stay strong. Stay strong, Mustapha.
Hurry!
Paddle!
God is the greatest!
Yunos!
Noni?
-Get up.
-I want my dad.
-Dad!
Dad!
Hey! You there!
Stop!
Go!
Go, Noni! Go!
Meor!
That's not wise.
Come!
There is no god
worthy of worship except Allah.
We're done here, Sir.
We're not done yet.
Sir?
There is a blood debt to be paid!
But we need
to go back as soon as possible.
Tomorrow,
the Japanese will surely come here.
We need to defend Sudong Island.
Some will fall,
but we will not waver
for the honor of our land.
We were born here,
so we will also be buried here.
All of us need to be ready.
Let them come!
The land of Sudong Island
will be bathed in blood!
My friends and I will make sure
Mustapha's death will not be in vain.
Fadhillah is too small
to accept a loss.
That'll teach her how to be stronger.
Let her cry
because crying does not mean weakness.
It hurts the most…
when the ones we love are hurt.
The same goes for this land.
Don't let it get hurt.
I won't let that happen.
The children and I
can only pray for you.
Because of you,
because of the children,
I must come home.
I will take that as a promise.
God hears the words
of those who praise Him.
God is great.
Peace be upon you all.
In the name of God.
Dear God,
please protect us
from disasters.
Keep us far away
from all the threats and betrayals.
Bring us
on the right path
that's fair
and impartial
in carrying out
the entrusted responsibilities.
Dear God, protect
the truth,
the fairness,
the unity,
peace and prosperity,
in this blessed country of ours.
Dear God,
give us the strength
in defending our homeland. O Allah!
Amen!
Split!
Where's Hikaru?
Attack!
Oh, God!
Tie him up!
-Move.
-Move!
Move!
Let go!
-Move.
-Move!
-Here!
-Sit.
-Sit!
-Shut up!
Shut up!
You want to die?
-Shut up!
-Bring the children in.
-Get inside.
-Let's go.
Honey!
Hey!
Yes, Sir!
Translate it.
All right, I get it.
Today, I may have lost,
but tomorrow, I shall win.
My army
is hundred times more than you.
Mr. Yamada said
he may have lost today,
but tomorrow,
he shall win.
Our army
is a hundred times more
than all of you.
You can chase me away.
But
I will surely come back tomorrow.
You can kill me,
but tomorrow,
more soldiers will be coming.
If you kill us,
more will come tomorrow.
But…
I'm giving you a chance to challenge me.
But
Mr. Yamada is giving you a chance
to challenge him.
If I lose, I won't come here anymore.
But
if you lose,
I'll kill everyone on this island.
If Mr. Yamada loses,
we will leave this island.
But if you lose,
we will kill everyone.
How is it?
What's your answer?!
What's your answer?
Alright!
I'll accept your challenge!
Yes. He accepted your challenge.
Hey!
This is your sword!
It hurts the most
when the ones we love are hurt.
Dad!
The same goes for this land.
Don't let it get hurt.
I will not let that happen.
-God is the greatest!
Praise be to God!
-Praise be to God!
Mr. Yamada.
As long as there is life,
I will not let this land be tarnished.
Tiger!
Ready!
No matter how hard the challenges are,
I will still protect it.
This is my promise to the people.
My promise to my religion.
I will not break it.
Even though my soul and body
are at stake,
I am never afraid
of the challenges that may come!
Tiger!
AFTER WORLD WAR II
MEOR ABDUL RAHMAN RETURNED TO SINGAPORE
AS AN OFFICER
IN THE CRIMINAL INVESTIGATION DEPARTMENT
SINGAPORE POLICE FORCE
-One!
-Huh! Huh!
I came here to work.
This will help us complete our work.
So, now,
are you still doing the right thing?
If I keep going,
I will find the truth.
THE END